Finding Aid for Eastwood Church of God (Kalamazoo, Mich.) records, 1937-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eastwood Church of God (Kalamazoo, Mich.) records 1937-1989
Eastwood Church of God (Kalamazoo, Mich.)
5 linear feet
921071 Ba 2
Kalamazoo, Michigan local Church of God congregation; general files consisting of church newsletter, annual reports, advisory council records, and subjects; church bulletins; scrapbooks of the women's missionary society; and audiotapes of church meetings; also photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church in 1991. (Donor No. 7968 )
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Eastwood Church of God was founded in 1937. The first service was held on February 7 at the YMCA in Kalamazoo, Michigan. The Church then moved to a rented storefront under the name of the Lovett Street Church of God a few weeks later. Reverend John Batdorf served as the first pastor. The first set of bylaws was adopted at a special congregational meeting on May 26, 1938.
In 1941, the congregation started meeting at the Faith Memorial Church with Rev. Batdorf serving as the main minister and the congregation of Faith Memorial providing the building. After sixteen months the congregation decided to rent space again, this time at the Eastside Community House.
1945 was an important year for Eastwood's congregation. The Reverend Weldon Lane became pastor of Eastwood and a building committee was elected. The building committee initiated the first Christmas dinner to raise money for the building fund. The Christmas dinner has become an important tradition with the congregation ever since. With funds from the Christmas dinner and other sources the congregation was able to purchase a house on 2929 East Main Street at Sunnyside Drive in Kalamazoo. The house was used for worship until a sanctuary was built. The sanctuary at the new property was dedicated in November 1946 and served as the congregation's home until 1991.
On August 22, 1948, Reverend B. Gale Hetrich and Bessie Hetrick assumed the pastorate at Eastwood. "Accents," the church newsletter was first published on March 26, 1950. Also in 1950 the church was able to provide a parsonage at 1233 Upland Dr.
Reverend Maurice Mauch became the third pastor at Eastwood in June 1956. In 1960, ground was broken for a major expansion of the church. The new sanctuary, dedicated April 9, 1961, seats 350 and also included modern teaching facilities able to accommodate 450 students.
In 1964 Reverend Harold Minkler assumed pastoral duties at Eastwood. During Reverend Minkler's tenure the congregation expanded with 180 individuals attending services regularly in 1969, the largest attendance in Eastwood's history. Since its first days music has played an integral part of Eastwood's religious life. An adult and children's choir has existed since the early years of the church. In the 1960s, church musical programs expanded with for example a youth choir created in 1964, the dedication of a new organ in the same year, and the presentation of the first octave of hand bells in 1965. Eastwood has added more hand bells to its musical program and it has become an important component in worship and concert.
The pastorate was undertaken by Reverend L. Spencer Spaulding in 1976. In 1978 Eastwood elected its first associate pastor, San Germany. The new pastor's responsibilities were music (choir director) and community outreach. In 1979, Dick Forsman was designated the first associate minister of youth.
Reverend Brian Hansen began pastoral duties in 1980. In 1984, a remodeling created two new Sunday school classrooms and a youth meeting space. Another remodeling in 1987 created new office facilities and a small fellowship hall. The sanctuary library and narthex were also renovated.
Eastwood Church of God has always been involved in the support of missionaries. The Ladies Missionary Society was founded in 1937. In 1972, the society disbanded and a mission outreach committee was formed. In 1964, Eastwood joined the Living Link program in support of Church of God missions. During the 1980s, many members of the congregation participated in work camps in Guyana and the Philippines.
Reverend John Henbruch, who took over pastoral duties in 1987, has had the responsibility of leading a church in flux. By 1987, regular attendance had decreased from a high of 180 to an average of 80 people on Sunday mornings. A special association meeting was called on April 9, 1989. The issue was to decide what direction the church should take in the future. Eastwood was feeling the pressure of a changing neighborhood. The outcome of the meeting was to focus targeting efforts on new members from the suburbs, which might necessitate changing the location of the worship center. The Eastwood Church of God sold its property in 1991, and moved to a rented building in a suburban location.
The records of the Eastwood Church of God (5 linear feet) span the years 1937 to 1989. The papers contain four series: General Files, Bulletins, Scrapbooks, and Audiotapes. The majority of records consist of minutes from the many committees at Eastwood.
Subjects:
Church buildings--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Church of God (Anderson, Ind.)--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Eastwood Church of God (Kalamazoo, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Church buildings--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Church of God (Anderson, Ind.)--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Churches--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Eastwood Church of God (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Japan.; Missions--Japan.; Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- General Files
  The General Files, arranged alphabetically by topic, contain the bulk of the records (2 linear feet). The files document the daily operations of Eastwood from 1937 to 1989. An incomplete run of "Accents," the Church newsletter, dates from 1965 to 1980. The majority of material in this series was generated by the various committees of Eastwood. The earliest committee minutes, kept together in a binder, are in the file titled "Minutes" located in box 2. The Advisory Council minutes cover the years 1941-1989 and detail the operation of Eastwood. "Annual Reports" (1939-1989) contain the previous year's budget and the proposed budget for the coming year. After 1956, the annual reports also contain yearly reports from many of the committees.
  The "Historical Materials" file within the General Files contains two church histories written for the congregation, covering the years 1937-1973 and 1937-1987 respectively. The "Historical Clippings" file includes various newspaper clippings concerning Eastwood. "Photographs" consists of labeled pictures of church members, pastors, and the sanctuary.
  - Accents (church newsletter)
    - 1965-1980, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Advisory Council
    - 1944-1989, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1957-1982, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1983-1989 (Box 2)
  - Board of Christian Education
    - 1975-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Budget Committee, Ad Hoc 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Building Committee 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Business Association 1980-1989 (Box 2)
  - Constitution and Bylaws (Box 2)
  - Faith-Promise Convention
    - 1977-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Finance and Property Committee
    - 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1984 (Box 2)
  - Historical Clippings (Box 2)
  - Historical Materials (Box 2)
  - Minutes 1937-1968 (Box 2)
  - Missions Outreach
    - 1977-1984 (Box 2)
    - Japanese Photographs, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Music and Worship Committee
    - 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - Pastor Harold Minkler's Orientation Materials 1964 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Planning and Development Committee 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Scholarship Committee 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Sunday School 1975-1981 (Box 2)
  - Women's Missionary Society
    - 1937-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1950 (Box 2)
  - Young Adult 1982 (Box 2)
  - Youth Program 1974-1980 (Box 2)
- Bulletins
  The Bulletins series (1 linear foot) contains church bulletins, 1964-1985. The bulletins list the program and activities for that Sunday of worship, and announcements. The bulletins are arranged chronologically.
  - 1964-1985, 23 folders (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series (1 linear foot) contains 5 scrapbooks from the Women's Missionary Society. The first includes pictures and historical information from 1937 to 1958. The second and third scrapbooks contain memorabilia of the Society, 1963-1964 and 1967-1968, respectively. The fourth and fifth scrapbooks contain memorabilia on Eastwood-sponsored missionary work in India from 1962 to 1968.
  - Women's Missionary Society
    - Historian's Scrapbooks
      - 1937-1958 (Box 4)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 4)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - India Missions
      - 1962-1967 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1968 (Box 4)
- Sound recordings
  The sound recordings series contains 29 audio tapes of activities at Eastwood. The majority of the tapes document musicals put on by the youth choir. Also documented are the reminiscences of Eastwood's first pastor. The identifications came from the tape boxes only.
  - Reel-to-reel audio tapes, 7 in., except where indicated
    - Undated
      - Unidentified (Box 5)
        (tape no. 1)
      - Dedication Service, Eastwood Church of God (Box 5)
        (tape no. 2)
      - Easter Music, Eastwood Church of God, 5 in. (Box 5)
        (tape no. 3)
      - Gaither Trio (Box 5)
        (tape no. 4)
      - Natural High, Dick Forsman (Box 5)
        (tape no. 5)
      - Organ Dedication with Paul & Rita Jo Yerden featuring the new Allan Church Organ (Box 5)
        (tape no. 6)
      - Tell It Like It Is (Box 5)
        (tape no. 7)
      - Tell It Like It Is, New Musicals, Boston (Box 5)
        (tape no. 8)
      - Van Oss, Bob, Republic District (Box 5)
        (tape no. 9)
      - Youth Program as recorded by George Cook (Box 5)
        (tape no. 10)
    - Dated
      - November 27, 1956 Mt. Pleasant, Dick Forsman (Box 5)
        (tape no. 11)
      - 1960 Youth Folk Music (Box 5)
        (tape no. 12)
      - 1961 Easter Cantata (Box 5)
        (tape no. 13)
      - 1962 MSYG, B.G. Trio (Box 5)
        (tape no. 14)
      - May 27, 1962, June 10, 1962 Combined Choir Concert (Box 5)
        (tape no. 15)
      - May 26, 1963 Combined Choir Concert, Eastwood Church of God (Box 5)
        (tape no. 16)
      - 1963 Christmas Play, 5 in. (Box 5)
        (tape no. 17)
      - 1964 Easter Evening, ECOG (Box 5)
        (tape no. 18)
      - 1964 Van Oss, Robert Concert, Eastwood Church of God (Box 5)
        (tape no. 19)
      - 1965 Easter Cantata, "No Greater Love" (Box 5)
        (tape no. 20)
      - 1967 Youth Christmas Cantata, Carol Christmas (Box 5)
        (tape no. 21)
      - 1968 Easter, "No Greater Love" (Box 5)
        (tape no. 22)
      - October 27, 1968 Folk Worship Service (Box 5)
        (tape no.23)
      - 1968 Minnesota Youth Convention, 5 in. (Box 5)
        (tape no. 24)
      - 1970 Michigan State Youth Convention (Box 5)
        (tape no. 25)
      - 1972 Fall Musical (Box 5)
        (tape no. 26)
      - 1974 "I'm Here, God's Here" (Box 5)
        (tape no. 27)
  - Cassette tapes
    - Undated, Memories of the Eastwood Church of God by John & Dora Baldorf (Box 5)
    - July 30, 1977 "What Faith-Promise Can Do For Your Church" the Rev. Bill Ellis (Box 5)